

HEALTH SCIENTIST - INFORMATICS

Respiratory Diseases Laboratory Branch, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA, USA

I am a scientist with 10+ years of experience in classical genetics, genomics, and evolutionary biology. My training includes using a range of tools - bioinformatics, population genetics, molecular evolution all with experimental design in mind. Over the years as my computational skills increased, the genomes of the organisms I work on have gotten smaller. Now, I work at the interface of public health, application development, and understanding organisms that can cause harm to humans with an empahsis of developing reproduciable research.

Education

University of Georgia Athens, GA

Ph.D. in Genetics 2015

University of North Carolina - Asheville

Asheville, NC

B.S. IN BIOLOGY

2010

Appointments

Centers for Disease Control and Prevention

Atlanta, GA

HEALTH SCIENTIST INFORMATICS

June 2022 - Current

- * General informatics for Legionella
 - Continued projects from previous position with ASRT, inc.

Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Contractor with ASRT Inc.

Atlanta, GA

BIOINFORMATICIAN II WITH DIVISION OF BACTERIAL DISEASES

November 2020 - June 2022

- * Interfacing with state public health laboratories (PHL)
 - Communicated with members of state PHL to provide guidenance regarding bionformatics and genomics for Legionella species
- * Refactored Legionella Species ID tool for broader compatibility and interfacing with Nextflow Tower
 - Removed structural design issues in original code that prevented expansion and adding of new functionalities
- * Development of method validation plan for Legionella Species ID tool
 - Researched and proposed statistically sound validation plan to test tool that uses next generation sequencing data
- * Phylogenetic and phylodynamic analyses for Legionella isolates of public health concern
 - Performing analyses and generating statistical summaries and visualizations
 - Writing and editing manuscripts for publication
 - Identifying scientific questions answerable with existing data
- * Developing or testing scripts and pipelines as necessary
 - Generated script to interact with National Center of Biotechnology Information for downloading all available Legionella genomes
 - Evaluated using Nextflow pipeline for mapping Legionella genomes
- * 60-day detail on Data Analytics and Visualization for Vaccine Task Force (April June 2021)
 - Produced weekly reports and consolidated steps for document creation to be reproducible via one script

Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Fellow with APHL

Atlanta, GA

ASSOCIATION OF PUBLIC HEALTH LABORATORIES (APHL) BIOINFORMATICS FELLOW

September 2019 - November 2020

- * Developing tinselR an Rshiny application for annotating outbreak trees
 - tinselR is an open-source downloadable package in the R language used for phylogenetic tree analysis and visualization
- * Participated in APHL core competency and leadership training
 - Gained skills and knowledge for a career in public health
- * 30-day detail on Routine Reporting for COVID-19 Response (June July 2020)
 - Produced daily and weekly reports for task force. Consolidated steps for document creation to be reproducible via one script

University of Georgia (UGA)

Athens, GA

October 2017 - August 2019

BENSASSON LAB POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

* Directed collaborative research with UGA graduate and undergraduate students

- * Collated and streamlined genome mapping for 1000 Saccharomyces cerevisiae isolates as lab resource
- * Used iterative approach to assign 400 genomes to well-defined populations using best practices for population genomics and phylogenetics
- * Resolved haplotypes for Candida albicans genomes with PacBio sequencing

Indiana University (IU)

Bloomington, IN

MOYLE LAB POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

June 2015 - September 2017

- * Directed research with faculty, graduate, and undergraduates at IU and with two external universities
- * Genome-wide study of factors that determine the likelihood of introgression for Solanum species
- * Streamlined genotyping to generate biological replicates. Validate data accuracy using technical replicates along with statistical analyses
- * Identified targeting rates and floral trait differences with biological & technical replicates in large-scale crossing project via statistical analyses

Skills_

Analytical

Data science, Experimental Design, Next Generation Sequencing, Genomics, High Performance Computing,

PROJECT MANAGEMENT, QUALITY CONTROL, REPRODUCIBLE RESEARCH, STATISTICS, TECHNICAL WRITING AND

DOCUMENTATION

Programming

AWK - PROFICIENT, BASH - EXPERT, PYTHON - EXPERT, R - EXPERT, RMARKDOWN - EXPERT, NEXTFLOW - PROFICIENT, GITHUB -

EXPERT

Publications

JAP Hamlin, T Nakov, A Williams-Newkirk

Announcements

TINSELR—AN R SHINY APPLICATION FOR ANNOTATING PHYLOGENETIC TREES

C. . - L. . t. - . . . L - t t - . . .

JAP Hamlin, MS Hibbins, LC Moyle

JAP Hamlin, NA Sherman, LC Moyle

JAP Hamlin, TJ Simmonds, ML Arnold

Evolution letters

ASSESSING BIOLOGICAL FACTORS AFFECTING POSTSPECIATION INTROGRESSION

G3

JAP Hamlin, GB Dias, CM Bergman, D Bensasson

2019

Phased Diploid Genome Assemblies for Three Strains of Candida albicans from Oak Trees

G.3

2020

TWO LOCI CONTRIBUTE EPISTASTICALLY TO HETEROSPECIFIC POLLEN REJECTION, A POSTMATING ISOLATING BARRIER BETWEEN

2017

SPECIES

Biological Journal of the Linnean

Society 2017

NICHE CONSERVATISM FOR ECOLOGICAL PREFERENCE IN THE LOUISIANA IRIS SPECIES COMPLEX

Journal of Heredity

NEUTRAL AND SELECTIVE PROCESSES DRIVE POPULATION DIFFERENTIATION FOR IRIS HEXAGONA

Journal of Hereuity

ML Arnold, AN Brothers, JAP Hamlin, SJ Taylor, NH Martin

Reticulate evolution

DIVERGENCE-WITH-GENE-FLOW—WHAT HUMANS AND OTHER MAMMALS GOT UP TO

2015

JAP Hamlin, ML Arnold

Ecology and Evolution

DETERMINING POPULATION STRUCTURE AND HYBRIDIZATION FOR TWO IRIS SPECIES.

201

ML Arnold, JAP Hamlin, AN Brothers, ES Ballerini, RS Singh, J Xu, ...

svstems

Atlanta, GA

NATURAL HYBRIDIZATION AS A CATALYST OF RAPID EVOLUTIONARY CHANGE

2012

ML Arnold, ES Ballerini, AN Brothers, JAP Hamlin, CDA Ishibashi, ...

Plant Ecology & Diversity

Rapidly evolving genes and genetic

THE GENOMICS OF NATURAL SELECTION AND ADAPTATION: CHRISTMAS PAST, PRESENT AND FUTURE (?).

201

Presentations _____

JAP Hamlin, ML Arnold

Talks

tinselR - An RShiny App for Phylogenetic Tree Annotation

CDC DATA VIZ DAY 2020

Start Writing Manuscripts in Rmarkdown

Atlanta, GA

GENOMICS INTEREST GROUP - TECHNICAL

2020

Build Shiny Apps	Athans CA
Warnell School of Forestry & Natural Resources Data Manipulation and Management course	Athens, GA 2018
Population Genomics of wild and domesticated yeast	Athens, GA
University of Georgia Enthusiasts of Diversity Genetics and Evolution	2018
No Easy D: Little Evidence for Introgression from Whole-Genome Data in Wild Solanum	Portland, OR
SOCIETY FOR THE STUDY OF EVOLUTION	2017
Epistasis for Postmating Prezygotic Isolation	Austin, TX
Society for the Study of Evolution Spatial, temporal, and genome-wide patterns of differentiation for the Louisiana iris	2016
species complex	Bloomington, IN
Indiana Unviversity Brown Bag	2015
What Drives Phenotypic and Genetic Divergence for Iris hexagona	Raleigh, NC
SOCIETY FOR THE STUDY OF EVOLUTION	2014
Comparative Phylogeography of Two Louisiana Irises	Snowbird, UT
SOCIETY FOR THE STUDY OF EVOLUTION	2013
Posters	
Combining Mash and NCBI Datasets via Nextflow for a Legionella Species Identification	Baltimore, MD
Tool American Society for Microbiology	2022
Hamlin JAP, Willby MJ, and Winchell JM	2022
Spread of Sequence Type ST222 from the Great Lakes Area to the US West Coast and	V 1 1
Europe	Yokohama, Japan
INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON LEGIONELLA	2022
 Kozak-Muiznieks NA, Hamlin JAP, Lucas C, and Willby MJ Tinsel - an Rshiny app for phylogenetic tree annotation 	Virtual
Association of Public Health Laboratories Annual Meeting	2020
Hamlin JAP and Williams-Newkirk A	
Tinsel - an Rshiny application for annotating outbreak trees	Canceled - Atlanta, GA
INTEGRATED FOODBORNE OUTBREAK RESPONSE AND MANAGEMENT	2020
Hamlin JAP and Williams-Newkirk A	D 1/1 0 04
Genetic admixture and the origins of clinical Saccharomyces cerevisiae yeast Fungal Genetics Conference	Pacific Grove, CA 2019
Hamlin JAP and Bensasson D	2013
Clinical Saccharomyces cerevisiae are admixed domesticated yeast	Holderness, NH
CELLULAR AND MOLECULAR FUNGAL BIOLOGY: GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCE	2018
Hamlin JAP and Bensasson D	
Higher Prevalence of Genetic Exchange Given Geographic Proximity Southeastern Population Ecology & Evolutionary Genetics.	Laural Hill, NC 2017
Hamlin JAP and Moyle LC	2017
Two Loci Contribute Epistastically to Heterospecific Pollen Tube Rejection, a Postmating	Davis, CA
Isolating Barrier Between Species	
SOLANACEAE CONFERENCE • Hamlin JAP and Moyle LC	2016
What Drives Phenotypic and Genetic Divergence for Iris hexagona	Boise, ID
BOTANICAL SOCIETY OF AMERICA	2014
Hamlin JAP and Arnold ML Comparative Phylogography of Two Louisians Ivis Species Ivis fully and Ivis hypricaulis	Commission (A4)
Comparative Phylogeography of Two Louisiana Iris Species: Iris fulva and Iris brevicaulis American Genetic Association	Guanajuato, Mexico 2011
Hamlin JAP, Brothers AN, Ballerini ES, and Arnold ML	2011

Packages _____

tinselR - An R package for visulizing and annotating phylogenetic trees

https://github.com/jennahamlin/tinselR

2019

mashwrapper - a Python tool for parsing mash results

https://github.com/jennahamlin/mashwrapper

Author and maintainer 20

Mentoring

AUTHOR AND MAINTAINER

University of Georgia graduate students

- E. Scopel Ferreira Da Costa
- J. Pena

University of Georgia undergraduate students

- T. Simmonds
- K. Miller
- J. Foley
- S. Duque
- B. Webb

Indiana University graduate students

- C. Jewell
- M. Gibson

Indiana University undergraduate students

- A. Huh
- J. Breisch
- S. Henderson
- L. Howser
- C. Plasterer
- D. Shukla
- S. Seo